Guide to the Aleksandar Sedmak Vesić Papers, 1956-1982 UA.29.02.0167
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Aleksandar Sedmak Vesić papers
1956-1982
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Vesić, Aleksandar Sedmak, 1924-
UA.29.02.0167
5 Linear Feet
Aleksandar Sedmak Vesić was a prominent civil engineer and Duke engineering professor. He is especially known for his work on soil properties and interaction with construction materials, as well as the use of explosives in excavation projects.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Collection Overview
The collection covers Aleksandar Sedmak Vesić's working and class papers. Included is research into soil mechanics, the application of engineering principles to construction materials, and the use of explosives in excavation projects. Vesić also lectured widely and participated in a large number of conferences and committees; materials related to those activities are also represented.
Biographical note
Aleksandar Sedmak Vesić was a Yugoslav-American geotechnical engineer and a major figure in the history of the Duke University Pratt Engineering School. Vesić specialized in soil mechanics, the application of engineering principles to construction materials, behavior of soils on the ocean floor, and the use of explosives in excavation projects.
Vesić studied at the University of Belgrade and received his doctorate in civil engineering. He worked at the Geotechnical Institute in Ghent, Belgium before moving to the United States in 1956. He began teaching in 1958 at the Georgia Institute of Technology. In 1963, he became a professor at Duke University, where he remained until his death in 1982. He was named Dean of the Pratt School of Engineering in 1974 and served as such until his death. In his honor, and in recognition for his contributions to the Engineering School, the position of department head of civil engineering bears his name, and the math, science, and technical library was renamed the Vesić Library in 1982, shortly after his death. This library carried his name until it closed in 2008.
Provenance
The Aleksandar Sedmak Vesić Papers were received by the Duke University Archives as a gift in January, 2005.
Duke University -- Faculty; Civil Engineering -- Research; Pratt School of Engineering (Duke University); Vesić, Aleksandar Sedmak, 1924-
- Papers, 1956-1982; 1
  - Bearing Capacity of Shallow Foundations, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Shallow Foundations, 1974; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Design of Pile Foundations, 1976, May (Box 1)
  - Pile Foundations, 1975 (Box 1)
  - NCHRP Pile Design, 1976; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Boston Lecture and NCHRP, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Technical Director's Operation Plan for Pre-Gondola II, 1967 May 17 (Box 1)
  - Logs and Lab Results (US Army), 1966; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Pre-Gondola III, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Pre-Gondola, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Cratering Excerpts, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Cratering Final Report, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Quarrying with Nuclear Explosives Final Draft, 1969 May (Box 1)
  - Wayne Clough Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Duke, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Bhathagar Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Cratering-Livermore, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Cratering-Livermore, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Quarrying, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Cratering, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Breakout Forces-Contract, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Research Proposals, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Cratering Lectures, 1968 (Box 1)
  - NASA, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Cratering, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Final Report, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - Ideas and Data, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Cratering Phase IV, Images, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Cratering, Phase III Images Report, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Administration, 1962-1965 (Box 1)
  - Cratering Monthly Reports, 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Expansion of Cavities Manuscript, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Excerpts II, 1956-1969; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Excerpts III, Undated; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Excerpts I, Undated; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Excerpts IV, Undated; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Russian Studies, Undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Duke Symposium, 1965-1967 (Box 2)
  - Duke Symposium, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Duke Accelerator, 1966 Summer (Box 2)
  - Duke Accelerator, 1966-1969 (Box 2)
  - Special Course-Wroth, 1975-1982 (Box 2)
  - Centrifuge, 1981 (Box 2)
  - HRB Committee B-6, 1965-1973; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - HRB Committee B-5, 1964-1975; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - HRB Committee B-1, 1966-1969 (Box 2)
  - HRB General, 1965-1973 (Box 2)
  - ASTM Subcommittee 11, 1967-1971 (Box 2)
  - ASTM Subcommittee 10, 1965-1969 (Box 2)
  - ASTM Atlantic City, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - School of Civil Engineering, Workload and Reports, 1958-1963 (Box 3)
  - Caracas, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Rice Lecture, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Europe, 1965-1968 (Box 3)
  - Montreal, 1963-1966 (Box 3)
  - Mexico City, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - Colorado, 1960 (Box 3)
  - San Francisco, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Scandinavia, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Miami, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - Mexico, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Denver, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Evanston, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Plowshare, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Ottawa, 1963 (Box 3)
  - ASCE Miami, 1966 (Box 3)
  - ASCE New York, 1964 (Box 3)
  - ASCE Chicago, 1969; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - ASCE Paris, 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - HRB Meeting, 1962-1969; 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Conference, New York, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Conference, Asphalt Pavements, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Civil Engineering 139 Intro to Soil Mechanics, Undated (Box 3)
  - Student Letters, 1963-1980; 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Logan Ritchie, 1961-1964 (Box 3)
  - Rigid Pavement Project, 1970; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - HRB Proposal, 1966 (Box 3)
  - NCHRP Project, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Georgia Project, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Introduction Lecture 5-5, Undated (Box 4)
  - Konrad Meyer, 1961-1969 (Box 4)
  - Introduction to Soil Mechanics, Undated; 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Mailing Lists, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - ASCE Papers Reviewed, 1967-1971 (Box 4)
  - ASCE Information Retrieval, 1968-1970 (Box 4)
  - NCHRP Advisory Panel, 1967 (Box 4)
  - ASCE Reviews, 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - ASCE Papers Reviewed, 1966-1967 (Box 4)
  - ASCE General, 1961-1974 (Box 4)
  - IABSE, 1966-1972 (Box 4)
  - ASCE Deep Foundations Committee, 1968-1978; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - HRB Papers Reviewed, 1967-1971 (Box 4)
  - NCHRP, 1971 (Box 4)
  - ASCE Reviews, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - Condolence Letters, Duke Community, Undated (Box 4)
  - Conference Papers, 1962-1977; 5 folders (Box 4)